Guide to the Judith Bregman Collection RG.013
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Judith Bregman Collection, 1966-1993
Bulk, 1966-1970
RG.013
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
4.5 Cubic feet collection contains 35 16mm films.
Judith Bregman was a professor of Physics at Polytechnic Institute of New York from 1957 until her death in 1978. During her time at Poly, she developed an interest in the preparation of instructional films, and is perhaps most well-known for her film 'Symmetry', which was created in 1966 in cooperation with Alan Holden, Richard Davisson, and Philip Stapp. This collection is comprised of 16 mm films Bregman helped to create and mass-produced educational films she used for classroom instruction. Some personal information about Bregman and her work is also included in the collection.
Bregman, Judith
Arrangement note
Series I - Series VII contain the personal papers of Judith Bregman, arranged by subject. Some of the correspondence, film distribution, and Bregman Film Account documents were maintained by physics professor Hellmut Juretschke after Bregman's death in 1978.
Series VIII contains 35 16mm films, arranged in their original order, as determined by Bregman, with miscellaneous audio/visual materials at the end.
Series IX contains 5 shipping containers in which some of the film reels were originally stored.
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists largely of the 16mm films which comprised Bregman's personal "film library" in the Physics Department at NYU-Poly. Included are 35 films of varying length and content; the some in color and some with audio. A number of the films, the ones to be found in Subseries A, were created by or for Polytechnic with the help of Bregman herself; the most notable of these is Symmetry. The remainder are films used by Bregman for class instruction and cover topics such as crystallography, quantum mechanics, and light scattering.
The collection also contains five film reel shipping containers in which the films were originally stored. The films are also accompanied by correspondence, grant proposals and contracts, reviews and articles of the films, film stills from Symmetry, documents from the Bergman Film Library account, and biographical materials about Bregman.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical/Historical note
Judith Bregman was a professor of Physics at Polytechnic Institute of New York from 1957 until her death in 1978. A graduate of Bryn Mawr and Cornell University, Bregman specialized in the areas of physical chemistry, x-ray crystallography, electron diffraction, and light scattering. During her time at Poly, she developed an interest in the preparation of instructional films, and is perhaps most well-known for her film 'Symmetry', which was created in 1966 in cooperation with Alan Holden, Richard Davisson, and Philip Stapp. The film received much attention, and was even shown at the Museum of Modern Art. She also participated in the making of other films, such as 'Aspects of Symmetry'. She died of cancer on October 2, 1978 at the age of 57.
Source: The above information is from Bregman's obituary in Physics Today, which can be found at Phillips, M. (1978). Judith Bregman. Physics Today. 31(12), 71. doi: 10.1063/1.2994888
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The film reels and containers were transferred to Bern Dibner Library of Technology & Science from the Physics Department in 1995 and stored in a glass and metal cabinet in the archives. Preliminary lists and finding aids were found in the cabinet when assessed in 2013.
Center for History of Physics (American Institute of Physics).; Davisson, Richard; Education Development Center.; Holden, Alan; Juretschke, Hellmut J.; National Science Foundation (U.S.).; Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn.; Polytechnic Institute of New York University -- Department of Physics.; Stapp, Philip; Audio-visual aids; Audio-visual materials; Brochures; Crystallography; Double pendulums; Educational films; Filmstrips; Grant proposals; Light Scattering; Photographs; Photography negatives; Physics; Quantum theory; Safety Film
- Series I: Biographical materials
  - Biographical Materials, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1966-1991
  Scope and Contents note
  Hellmut Juretschke (then head of the physics department) received and responded to some correspondence after Judith Bregman's death, therefore some correspondence addressed to Bregman appears in Juretschke's folders of correspondence. Some death notices and Juretschke's speech at Bregman's memorial are also included in folder 2.
  - Bregman, Judith, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Juretschke, Hellmut -- Bregman memorial and condolences, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Juretschke, Hellmut -- Inter-Office correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Juretschke, Hellmut -- Bregman memorial film library, Bulk, 1978; 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Juretschke, Hellmut -- Bregman film distribution, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III: Symmetry and Aspects of Symmetry
  - Proposal and grant -- National Science Foundation (NSF), 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Production and distribution contracts, Bulk, 1966-1970; 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles and reviews, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Awards, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Screening announcements, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Programs and brochures, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Responses from educators, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Responses from students, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Film stills -- Negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Film stills -- Negatives and 5"x7" test prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Flim stills -- Color photographs (2.75" x 3.5"), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Film stills -- Color photographs (8" x 10"), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Film stills -- Taped together, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Other films
  - Bregman films: "A Computer Animated Film on the Quantum Mechanical Harmonic Oscillator," "The Packet of an Uncertain Gaussian," and "Swinging Quanta", 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Moire patterns, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Physics teaching films -- Information and brochures, 1965-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series V: Bregman film distribution, Bulk, 1980-1984; 1972-1991
  - Correspondence -- 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence -- 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence -- 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Inter-Office correspondence and receipts, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Advertising, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series VI: Judith Bregman Film Account, 1977-1993
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bregman Film Account -- 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Schwartz Memorial Library Fund, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series VII: Original film library lists
  - Film lists found in Bregman film cabinet, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series VIII: Audio/Visual Materials, undated
  Contains 35 16mm films. The first subseries contains films produced by Bregman through grant-funded projects while at Polytechnic, including "Symmetry." Additional subseries are comprised of films used by Bregman for class instruction, or which were otherwise part of her film library. All films are organized according to their original groupings as determined by Bregman.
  - Subseries A: Polytechnic Films, undated
    - Symmetry, Copy A, undated; Adhesive residue on leader, red shift, vinegary (Reel 1, Box 2)
    - Symmetry, Copy B, undated; Adhesive residue on leader, red shift, vinegary (Reel 2, Box 2)
    - Symmetry, Copy 3, 1973; Adhesive residue on leader, severe red shift, slightly powdery (Reel 3, Box 2)
    - Symmetry, Copy 4, undated; Marked as scratched, red shift, a little warped (Reel 4, Box 2)
    - Aspects of Symmetry, undated; severe red shift, vinegary (Reel 5, Box 2)
    - Aspects of Symmetry, from A & B rolls, undated; Marked 'sprocket holes bad last 2-3 minutes'; couldn’t open (Reel 6, Box 2)
    - Swinging Quanta, Copy 1, 1976; Adhesive residue on leader, otherwise fair (Reel 7, Box 2)
    - Swinging Quanta, Copy 2, 1976 (Reel 8, Box 2)
    - The Packet of an Uncertain Gaussian, Copy 1, undated; Marked 'sprocket holes damaged', adhesive residue on leader, red shift, vinegary (Reel 9, Box 2)
    - The Packet of an Uncertain Gaussian, Copy 2, undated; adhesive residue (Reel 10, Box 2)
  - Subseries B: General, 1968-1978
    - Frames of Reference, undated (Reel 11, Box 3)
    - Powers of Ten, 1978 (Reel 12, Box 3)
    - Million to One, undated (Reel 13, Box 3)
  - Subseries C: One-Dimensional Scattering, undated
    - QP1: Barriers: Scattering in One Dimension, undated (Reel 14, Box 3)
    - QP2: Wells: Scattering in One Dimension, undated (Reel 15, Box 3)
    - QP3: Edge Effects: Scattering in One Dimension, undated (Reel 16, Box 3)
    - QP4: Momentum Space: Scattering in One Dimension, undated (Reel 17, Box 3)
    - QP5: Free Wave Packets, undated (Reel 18, Box 3)
    - QP6: Packet in a Perfect Crystal Wave Packets in Periodic Potentials, undated (Reel 19, Box 3)
    - QP7: Packet Incident on Crystal, undated (Reel 20, Box 3)
    - QP8: Scattering From Impurities: Wave Packets in Periodic Potentials, undated (Reel 21, Box 3)
    - QP10: Individual Events in One-Dimensional Scattering, undated (Reel 22, Box 3)
    - QP15: Particle in a Box, undated (Reel 23, Box 3)
  - Subseries D: Coupled Pendulums, undated
    - OS-5, OS-6, OS-7: Sand Pendulum I: Point Suspension, II: Saddle Suspension, III: Short Saddle Suspension, undated (Reel 24, Box 3)
    - OS-8, OS-9: Forad Damped Harmonic Oscillators, undated (Reel 25, Box 3)
    - OS-10: Ring of Coupled Pendulums: Normal Modes, undated (Reel 26, Box 3)
  - Subseries E: Quantum Mechanics, 1965-1978
    - Scattering of Quantum Mechanical Wave Packets from Potential Well and Barrier, undated (Reel 27, Box 4)
    - Q. M. Scattering, 1965 (Reel 28, Box 4)
    - Quantum Mechanical Harmonic Oscillators Seq 4, undated (Reel 29, Box 4)
  - Subseries F: Solid State, undated
    - Experiments with the Bubble Model of a Metal Structure, undated (Reel 30, Box 4)
  - Subseries G: Crystallography, undated
    - Analyse et Synthese De Frourier, undated (Reel 31, Box 4)
    - HMX Alpha-Beta Stereo, undated (Reel 32, Box 4)
  - Subseries H: Miscellaneous Films, 1968-1978
    - Hurricane Watch 1968, edges look pretty chewed up, especially the non-sprocket edge. It looks like it could be mold, but I highly doubt that. Maybe some projector or mishandling damage? Severe red shift; Vinegar Syndrom (Reel 33, Box 4)
    - Volta and Electricity, undated; red shift, vinegary (Reel 34, Box 4)
    - Weather in Motion #20 (From ATS-I Synchronous Satellite), undated (Reel 35, Box 4)
    - "50", severe red shift, slightly warped; vinegar syndrome (Reel 36, Box 4)
  - Slide Presentation with Audio Cassette, 1984 (Cassette 1, Box 4)
    Consists of one "Moments of Discovery" book including Teacher's Guides and Scripts for units on the discovery of fission, and pulsars. Also included are two audio cassette tapes and 20 black and white slides, some exhibiting damage.
- Series IX: Original shipping containers, 1974-1986
  Five film reel shipping containers constructed of carboard with reinforced metal corners, label slots, and cotton buckles.
  - Small Shipping Container 1, undated (Object 1, Box 5)
  - Small Shipping Container 2, undated (Object 2, Box 5)
  - Small Shipping Container 3, undated (Object 3, Box 5)
  - Large Shipping Container 1, undated (Object 4, Box 5)
  - Large Shipping Container 2, undated (Object 5, Box 5)